Finding Aid for Coalition of Indian-Controlled School Boards Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00696
Sophia Smith Collection
Coalition of Indian-Controlled School Boards Oral History Project Records
1967- 2009
Sophia Smith Collection
Reynolds, Gerald W.
SSC.MS.00696
1 boxes (1.25 linear feet)
97 oral histories (audio recordings and partial transcripts)
Oral history interviews with individuals who made "unrivaled contributions to Indian parental and community control of Indian education." The collection includes audio recordings, partial transcripts, related correspondence and published documents. A large percentage of the interviews are with women and many who were involved in the Indian rights movement, including Rebecca Adamson, the first field coordinator for the coalition.
Biographical / Historical
According to oral historian Jerry Reynolds, who conducted the 60 interviews that comprise the heart of this collection, "The Archival interviews and research on the Coalition of Indian Controlled School Boards fill a gaping empty page in the contemporary annals of Indian Country, and of America's social justice movement at large. The interviews contain a unique, otherwise unknowable history. From before its official incorporation in 1971 to its demise in 1981, the Coalition made unrivaled contributions to Indian parental and community control of Indian education. In 1974, in Education and the American Indian: The Road to Self-Determination Since 1928, scholar Margaret Connell Szasz wrote, 'In its first year, the coalition provided technical assistance in all aspects of education for Indian school boards, communities, and organizations, and served as a clearing house for information on legislation and other matters pertaining to Indian education. Less than two years after it was formed, CICSB was serving eighty-seven schools and organizations.' In the same year, Vine Deloria Jr. put the case for the Coalition in still stronger terms. Writing in 'The Indian Affair' that of the organizations forged to 'carry the fight to the Bureau' after the Bureau of Indian Affairs' decision to outflank self-determination on the battleground of educational programs and policies, Deloria states: 'The most important of these [organizations] is the Coalition of Indian Controlled School Boards ... now working with over a hundred local Indian school boards in trying to take over the education of reservation and urban Indian children. The Coalition is the most efficient and sophisticated organization that Indian country has ever seen and is far more capable than the Indian political groups ... in getting changes made.' Deloria went on to describe the Coalition's successful lawsuit against President Richard M. Nixon's administration for the release of impounded Indian education funds. 'The Coalition thus accomplished more for Indians in one lawsuit than the activists have by any of their celebrated events, for the monies went directly into Indian controlled school districts and allowed the reservation people to begin development of their educational institutions. The year after Szasz and Deloria wrote their contemporary testimonials, the Coalition was the principal reason the '638' law of 1975 is entitled 'The Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act.'"
Scope and Contents
The collection includes interviews with individuals who made "unrivaled contributions to Indian parental and community control of Indian education." There are audio recordings, abstracts and partial transcripts most interviews. A large percentage of the interviews are with women, many of whom were involved in the Indian rights movement, including Rebecca Adamson who was the first field coordinator for the coalition (note: Rebecca Adamson's papers are also housed in the Sophia Smith Collection). According to oral historian Jerry Reynolds, 46 of the 97 interviewees were women. "Women played a decisive role in the Coalition's accomplishments both as committed parents and political catalysts."
The collection also includes audio recordings of the conference: Struggle for Self-Determination in Education: Its On-going Value, at Wyoming Indian High School, 2006; plus related correspondence, memos, articles, published and unpublished manuscripts, books, legal documents, and government reports.
Conditions Governing Access
A few of the oral histories have restrictions on access to the full interview. Please see the notes attached to an individual interview for information about restrictions that apply to it.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collections was donated to the SSC by Gerald Reynolds in 2013.
Accruals
This collection is comprised of the following accessions, some of which may not have accession records. Accession numbers: 12S-44. Accessions were received on the following dates: 2012-07-12.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. This collection also contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
Other Finding Aids
This finding aid currently includes only a partial contents listlisting of the contents interviews. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Education -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indians of North America -- Education -- History -- Sources; Indians of North America -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indian reservations -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indian rights; Indian women -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Oral history -- Archival resources; Adamson, Rebecca; Pine Hill School (Pine Hill, N.M.); Alexander, Russ; Bixby, Norma; Blake, Marilyn; Boivin, Cindy; Cline,Eddie; Cline, Eunice; Corn, Ronnie; Davids, Louise; Dean, Bobo; Dean, Barbero; Dickenson, Irene; Dixon, Barbara; Dodge, Carol; Dodge, Richard; Dodge, Paula; Edmo, Maxine; Gerard, Forrest; Gillette, Vance; Gipp, David; Gress, Betty; Gross, Mike; Jensen, Cecil Ann (nee Perry); Kickingbird, Kirke; Kickingbird, Lynn; Kilberg, Bobbie (Greene); Kills Straight, Birgil; Little Bear, Richard; Lovesee, Alan; Manning-Dick, Claire; Manuelito, Kathryn; Manuelito, Larry; McCullough, Gloria; McMinds, Guy; Patterson, Harold; Nelson, Bob; Norton, Marcellene; One Feather, Gerald; Plummer, Abe; Pourier, Marilyn; Pyatskowit, Al; Redman, Al; Roberts, Bill"Lee"; Robinson, David; Sahmaunt, Ace; Schierbeck, Helen; Shawanokasic, Leslie; Skenadore, Lynn; Skenadore, Mike; Small, Dorothy; Tiger, Buffalo; Tomasich, John; Tourtillot, Bernadette; Peters, Carrie; Wanatee, Don; Wanatee, Priscilla; Barlow, Earl; Black Elk, Charlotte; Bleskin, Charles; Bleskin, Meredith; Caldwell, Alan; Chromy, John; Demmert, William; Erlich, Suzy; Ghost Bear, John; Gray, Gerald; Honaker, Keith; Harris, LaDonna; Lone Fight, Ed; Marble, Don; Miller, David Jonesy; Steenberg, Janis Herman; articles; Bibliographies; Bills (Legislative records); Books; CD-Roms; clippings; correspondence; Court cases; DVD video discs; Electronic records; Government documents; Legal documents; Oral histories; press releases; Proceedings; Publications; reports; Computer media; Coalition of Indian-Controlled School Boards; Reynolds, Gerald W.; Reynolds, Gerald W.
- "Michael Gross papers" (attorney for CICSB): correspondence, memos, reports, 1971-1977; Gross, Michael (1)
- Correspondence and press releases, 1978-1981 (1)
- "Martha L. Hippe papers": correspondence, research, newspaper articles, 1970-2006 (1)
- Martha L. Hippe, "The Last Line Drawn in Wind River Sand: The History of an American Indian Struggle to Establish a Reservation School District" (1)
- Harold Patterson, "The Taholah Community School", 1976; Patterson, Harold (1)
- "The Indian Way to Education: an historical descriptive study of the Menominee Community School" (1)
- Articles re: Indian education, 1970-1975 (1)
- Legal documents and press release for Redman, et al v. John Ohina, Acting Commissioner of Education, Wyoming, 1973 (1)
- Keahna, et al v. The South Tama County Community School District, 1969 (1)
- Office of the Inspector General, Review of Federal grants to CICSB, 1978-1981 (1)
- Text of Public Law 93-638, aka the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act, 1975 (1)
- "Indian Education: A National Tragedy – A National Challenge," Presidential statement and government report, 1969-1970 (1)
- Transcript of regional meetings on president's Indian message, 1970 July 8 (1)
- CICSB oral history transcripts and abstracts, 2005-2009 (1)
- Buffalo Tiger and Harry A. Kersey, Jr., Buffalo Tiger: A Life in the Everglades, 2002 (1)
- Margaret Connell Szasz, Education and the American Indian, 1977 (1)
- Government reports: Hearings on the Education of Indian Children, 5 vols., 1969 (1)
- Vine Deloria, Jr., The Indian Affair, photocopy pp. 79-87, 1974 (1)
- Bobbie Greene Kilberg, thesis, Yale Law School, 1969; Kilberg, Bobbie (1)
- Memo and report on Indian hearings from the National Council on Indian Opportunities, Office of the Vice President, 1971 January 18 (1)
- Bobbie Greene Kilberg, memo and John Erlichman, and article in the Washington Post, "Indian Affairs Hearings: Beyond the Destruction", 1970 June 1 and 1972 December 2; Kilberg, Bobbie (1)
- Interview transcripts and notes (1)
  - Rebecca Adamson Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 March; Adamson, Rebecca; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
  - Russ Alexander Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Alexander, Russ; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Carol Barbero Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 May; Barbero, Carol; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Earl Barlow Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2009 July; Barlow, Earl; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Norma Bixby Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Bixby, Norma; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Charlotte Black Elk Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 April; Black Elk, Charlotte; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Marilyn Blake Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Blake, Marilyn; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Charles Bleskan Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Bleskan, Charles; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Meredith Bleskan Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 March; Bleskan, Meredith; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Cindy Boivin Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Boivin, Cindy; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Alan Caldwell Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Caldwell, Alan; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - John Chromy Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 January; Chromy, John; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Eddie Cline Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Cline, Eddie; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Eunice Cline Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Cline, Eunice; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Ronnie Corn Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Corn, Ronnie; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Louise Davids Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Davids, Louise; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Thomas Davis Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 March; Davis, Thomas; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - S. Bobo Dean Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 May; Dean, S. Bobo; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - William G. Demmert Jr. Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 March; Demmert, William, Jr.; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Irene Dickenson Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Dickenson, Irene; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Barbara Dixon Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Dixon, Barbara; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Carol Dodge Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Dodge, Carol; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
    The narrator has requested that this interview be closed until 10/1/28. The narrator has requested that this interview not be made available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
  - Paula Dodge Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Dodge, Paula; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Richard Dodge Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Dodge, Richard; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Maxine Edmo Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Edmo, Maxine; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Suzy Erlich Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2009 November; Erlich, Suzy; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Forrest Gerard Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 September; Gerard, Forrest; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - John Ghostbear Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 October; Ghostbear, John; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Vance Gilette Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Gilette, Vance; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - David Gipp Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Gipp, David; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Gerald Gray Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 May; Gray, Gerald; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Betty Gress Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 October; Gress, Betty; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Michael Gross Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August and October, 2006 February; Gross, Michael; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - LaDonna Harris Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 February; Harris, LaDonna; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Keith Honaker Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Honaker, Keith; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Cecil Ann Jensen Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Jensen, Cecil Ann; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Kirke Kickingbird Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 October; Kickingbird, Kirke; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Lynn Kickingbird Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 October; Kickingbird, Lynn; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Bobbie Green Kilberg Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 May; Kilberg, Bobbie; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Birgil Kills Straight Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Kills Straight, Birgil; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Richard Little Bear Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Little Bear, Richard; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Ed Lone Fight Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Lone Fight, Ed; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Alan Lovesee Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 May; Lovesee, Alan; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Claire Manning-Dick Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Manning-Dick, Claire; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Kathryn Manuelito Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 February; Manuelito, Kathryn; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Larry Manuelito Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 February; Manuelito, Larry; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Don Marble Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 March; Marble, Don; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Gloria McCullough Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; McCullough, Gloria; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Guy McMinds Interviewed by Jerry Reynolds, 2006 January; McMinds, Guy; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Harold Patterson Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Patterson, Harold; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - David Miller Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Miller, David; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Bob Nelson Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Nelson, Bob; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Marcellene Norton Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Norton, Marcellene; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Gerald One Feather Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 May; One Feather, Gerald; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Gianna Orozco Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Orozco, Gianna; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Carrie Peters Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Peters, Carrie; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Abe Plummer Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Plummer, Abe; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Marilyn Pourier Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Pourier, Marilyn; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Al Pyatskowit Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Pyatskowit, Al; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
    The narrator has requested that this interview not be made available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
  - Ramah Navajo School Board: Dedication of Pine Hill School Dormitory, 2005 September 30 (1)
  - Al Redman Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 May; Redman, Al; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Bill Roberts Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 January; Roberts, Bill; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - David Robinson Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 March; Robinson, David; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Hershel Sahmaunt Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 October; Sahmaunt, Hershel; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Helen Scheirbeck Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Scheirbeck, Helen; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Leslie Shawanokasic Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Shawanokasic, Leslie; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Lynn Skenadore Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Skenadore, Lynn; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Mike Skenadore Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Skenadore, Mike; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Dorothy Small Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 September; Small, Dorothy; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Janice Steenberg interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2007 March; Steenberg, Janice; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Buffalo Tiger Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2006 June; Tiger, Buffalo; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - John Tomasich Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Tomasich, John; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Bernadette Tourtillot Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Tourtillot, Bernadette; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Don Wanatee Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Wanatee, Don; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
  - Priscilla Wanatee Interviewed by Gerald Reynolds, 2005 August; Wanatee, Priscilla; Reynolds, Gerald W. (1)
- Digital audio recordings and transcripts of interviews, 70 oral histories (73 digital audio files and 35 (partial) transcripts); 5 items (audio compact discs) (1)
- Wind River Conference: "The Struggle for Self Determination in Education - Its Ongoing Value", 2006 February 3-4; 13 items (audio compact discs); 13 items (digital audio wav files) (1)